Guide to the Ernst Cassirer Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
#158 - Naturalistische und hum. Begründung der Kulturphilosophie, Wien, Dez. 1936, Kulturbund [?]; Wandlungen der Staatsgesinnung und der Staatstheorie in der deutschen Geistesgeschichte; Ein unbeschriebender Vortrag [Box 47, folder 923]
#159 - Symbolische Formen I [Box 23, folder 433]
#160 - Burckhardt-Aufsatz: Material [Box 37, folder 719]
#161 - Descartes-Leibniz-Vico: Übungen, Jan./Februar 1935, London, Warburg Inst.; Vom Einfluss der Sprache und die naturwissenschaftlich. Begriffsbildung [Box 38, folder 744]
#162 - Goethe und Kant, German Department, 25.I.44, Material; Jewish Const. Record (Material) [Box 40, folder 795]
#163 - Gruppentheorie (Philos. Club, 5.6.44) [Box 42, folder 828]
#164 - Ernst Cassirer: Goethe (Material) [Box 40, folder 802]
#165 - Vorarbeiten zur Philosophie der Aufklärung I [Box 21, folder 390]
#166 - Jakob Burckhardt-Aufsatz, Handschr. Orig. + 2 Durchschläge; Orig.-typescript sent to American Scholar 10/4 44 [Box 39, folder 766]
#167 - Structuralism in modern Linguistics (Material + Konzept) [Box 51, folder 1018]
#168 - Galileo's Platonism Manuscript, 1945 [Box 40, folder 780]
#169 - 4. Juli 1901, Aufgabe für das Preisausschreiben der Akademie Berlin [Box 15, folder 284]
#170 - Die Einheit der Wissenschaft, 2 Vorträge, Radio, Berlin, 1931 [Box 39, folder 753]
#171 - BLANK [Box 46, folder 921]
#172 - Enlightenment, English Edition, Material: 17-18th Century [Box 22, folder 423]
#173 - Thomas Mann-Aufsatz, Umarbeitung, New York [Box 46, folder 913]
#174 - Antrittsvorlesung, Göteborg, Okt. 1935 [Box 36, folder 701]
#175 - H. v. Kleist u. die kantische Philosophie [Box 13, folder 252]
#176 - Substanzbegriff [Box 33, folder 631]
#177 - BLANK [Box 47, folder 927]
#178 - Idee u. Gestalt [Box 13, folder 247]
#179 - Vorarbeiten zur Philosophie der Aufklärung II [Box 21, folder 400]
#180 - Philos. d. symb. Formen II [Box 27, folder 517]
#181 - Philos. d. symbol. Formen, I/II, Vorarbeiten und Paralipomena [Box 24, folder 440]
#182 - Philos. d. symb. Formen III [Box 27, folder 522]
#183 - BLANK [Box 57, folder 1127]
#184 - Symbolische Formen IV, Vorarbeiten, Manuskript av Föreningsgatan 11 [Box 31, folder 599]
#185 - Philos. d. symb. Formen II [Box 26, folder 492]
#186a- Material z. Erkenntnisproblem I/II [Box 2, folder 34]
#186b- Material z. Erkenntnisproblem I/II [Box 3, folder 46]
#186c- Material z. Erkenntnisproblem I/II [Box 4, folder 54]
#187 - Platonismus in England, Shaftesbury, Vortrag [Box 32, folder 613]
#188 - Indiv. u. Kosmos [Box 14, folder 259]
#189 - Geschichte der antiken Philosophie, Dessois Lehrbuch [Box 12, folder 231]
#190 - Erkenntnisproblem 1 und 2, ungeordnet [Box 4, folder 61]
#191 - Kants Leben und Lehre [Box 14, folder 271]
#192 - Freiheit und Form (Manuskript) [Box 11, folder 220]
#193 - Manuskript, Erkenntnisproblem I und II, ungeordnet [Box 4, folder 64]
#194 - Substanzbegriff [Box 34, folder 644]
#195 - Manuskript von "Erkenntnisproblem Bd. III" [Box 8, folder 147]
#196 - Kant und das Problem der Metaphysik (Heidegger); Kant und die moderne Biologie (Marc-Wogau); Das Freiheitsproblem als Zentrum der Kantischen Philosophie [Box 39, folder 770]
#197 - Die Schule von Cambridge [Box 32, folder 611]
#198 - Thomas Manns Goethe-Bild von Ernst Cassirer [Box 46, folder 915]
#199 - Realitätstheorie [Box 35, folder 663]
#200 - Der Begriff der symb. Formen im Aufbau der Geisteswissenschaften, Vortrag, 24.XI.1921, Warburg [Box 37, folder 711]
#201 - Erkenntnisproblem I, 2. Auflage [Box 7, folder 127]
#202 - Erkenntnisproblem I, Aufl. II [Box 6, folder 115]
#203 - BLANK [Box 54, folder 1083]
#204 - Der jünge Goethe, 1940/41 [Box 41, folder 806]
#205 - The Technique of our Modern Political Myth [Box 51, folder 1027]
#206 - Machiavelli-Vorles. (Columbia) (Paralip); Machiavelli-Kapitel, Zusätze und Umarbeit. (Handschrift) [Box 46, folder 912]
#207 - Hermann Cohen [Box 38, folder 724]
#208 - Cassirer: "Zur Erkenntnistheorie der Kulturwissenschaften," Vortrag (Göteborg, Lund), April 1941 [Box 52, folder 1058]
#209 - Aufsatz: Language and Art (Cornell-U. 23/4 42); Language, Myth, Art (Letztes Sprach-Seminar 11.V.42) [Box 45, folder 890]
#210 - Newton and Leibniz Ms. [Box 47, folder 926]
#211 - Spinoza-Vortrag, H. Cohen, Oxford Philos. Society, June 1934 [Box 50, folder 1005]
#212 - Lecture: Connecticut College, 3. April 1944; Vortrag: New London, 1944, Philosophy of History [Box 47, folder 944]
#213 - BLANK [Box 40, Folder 798]
#214 - Philosophy Club, April 1945, Engl. Manuskript des Gruppenbegriffs; Einleitung am morgen des 13. April 1945 geschrieben [Box 41, folder 823]
#215 - Gruppentheorie (engl.), Neues Typescr. + Paral. [Box 42, folder 827]
#216 - Kant u. Rousseau [Box 32, folder 625]
#217 - Goethe und die Kantische Philosophie, manuscript und typescript, Germ. Club, Yale, Febr. 1944 [Box 32, folder 626]
#218 - Vortrag: Kant und die modernen Biologie [Box 44, folder 870]
#219 - "Educational value of art" [Box 39, folder 751]
#220 - BLANK [Box 47, folder 934]
Philosophy, German; Philosophy, Modern; Germany -- Intellectual life -- 20th Century; Authors, German; Philosophers; Plato; Cassirer, Ernst, 1874-1945; Cassirer, Fritz, 1871-1926; Cohen, Hermann, 1842-1918; Descartes, René, 1596-1650; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955; Ficino, Marsilio, 1433-1499; Galilei, Galileo, 1564-1642; Gellert, Christian Fürchtegott, 1715-1769; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832; Gundolf, Friedrich, 1880-1931; Hägerström, Axel, 1868-1939; Hegel, Georg Wilhelm Friedrich, 1770-1831; Heidegger, Martin, 1889-1976; Herder, Johann Gottfried, 1744-1803; Humboldt, Wilhelm von, 1767-1835; Kant, Immanuel, 1724-1804; Kristeller, Paul Oskar, 1905-1999; Leibniz, Gottfried Wilhelm, Freiherr von, 1646-1716; Machiavelli, Niccolò, 1469-1527; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955; Natorp, Paul, 1854-1924; Newton, Isaac, 1642-1727; Pico della Mirandola, Giovanni, 1463-1494; Rousseau, Jean-Jacques, 1712-1778; Scheler, Max, 1874-1928; Schelling, Friedrich Wilhelm Joseph von, 1775-1854; Schiller, Friedrich, 1759-1805; Schweitzer, Albert, 1875-1965; Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of, 1671-1713; Spinoza, Benedictus de, 1632-1677; Stern, William, 1871-1938; Thorild, Thomas, 1759-1808
- Books, 1902-41; Series I; 14.25; (35 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Books (Boxes 1-35), is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - BIBLIOGRAPHY
    - Yale University Press list, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Kircher list, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AXEL HÄGERSTRÖM
    - Envelope #110
      - Research notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Envelope #85
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - Envelope #84c
      - Draft, typescript (incomplete), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6a)
      - Draft, typescript, carbon (incomplete), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6b)
      - [The above two folders consist of photocopies. The originals may be found in Box 32, folders 623-24 and are now the reverse pages for the holograph draft of Rousseau-Kant- Goethe: Two Essays .]
  - DESCARTES: LEHRE--PERSÖNLICHKEIT--WIRKUNG
    - Envelope #111
      - Research notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - I. Teil. "Grundproblem des Cartesianismus"
      - Envelope #88
        - "Die Idee der 'Einheit der Wissenschaft' in der Philosophie Descartes'," draft, holograph, corrected (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - II. Teil. "Descartes und sein Jahrhundert"
      - Envelope #90
        - "Descartes' 'Recherche de la Vérité par la lumière naturelle,'" draft, holograph, corrected, 1938 May 24-26 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - II. Teil. "Descartes und Königin Christina von Schweden"
      - Envelope #91
        - I-III (partial), draft A, holograph, corrected, 1938 Mar 2-18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        - III (partial)-V, draft A, holograph, corrected, 1938 Mar 2-18 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Envelope #89
        - I. "Das Verhältnis von Descartes und Königin Christina von Schweden als geistesgeschichtliches Problem," draft B, typescript, corrected, 1938 May (Box 1, Folder 13)
        - II. "Der 'universelle Theismus' und das Problem der natürlichen Religion im 17. Jahrhundert," draft B, typescript, corrected, 1938 May (Box 1, Folder 14)
        - III. "Die Renaissance des Stoizimus in der Ethik des 16. und 17. Jahrhunderts," draft B, typescript, corrected, 1938 May (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - IV. "Die Philosophie Descartes' und ihre Stellung innerhalb des französischen Klassizismus," draft B, typescript, corrected, 1938 May (Box 1, Folder 16)
        - V. "Königin Christinas 'Sentiments heroïques' und das heroische Ideal des 17ten. Jahrhunderts," draft B, typescript, corrected, 1938 May (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Envelope #91
        - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - DETERMINISMUS UND INDETERMINISMUS
    - Envelope #151
      - Research notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
      - Research notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 21-25)
    - Envelope #93
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 26-33)
  - DAS ERKENNTNISPROBLEM IN DER PHILOSOPHIE
    - 1. Auflage, 1. u. 2. Bände
      - Envelope #186a
        - Research notes, ca. 1906 (Box 2, Folder 34-39)
        - Research notes, ca. 1906 (Box 3, Folder 40-45)
      - Envelope #186b
        - Research notes, ca. 1906 (Box 3, Folder 46-53)
      - Envelope #186c
        - Research notes, ca. 1906 (Box 4, Folder 54-60)
    - 1. Auflage, 1. Band
      - Envelope #190
        - Vorrede zur ersten Auflage: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 4, Folder 61)
        - Inhalts-Verzeichnis: draft, holo- graph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 4, Folder 62)
        - Einleitung: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 4, Folder 63)
      - Envelope #193
        - 1. Buch, 1.-3. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 4, Folder 64-67)
      - Envelope #190
        - 2. Buch, 1.-2. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 4, Folder 68-71)
          Related Archival Materials note
          See also: Oversize, Box 59, folder 1131
      - Envelope #193
        - 2. Buch, 3. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 4, Folder 72)
        - 3. Buch, 1.-2. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 5, Folder 73-76)
      - Envelope #190
        - 3. Buch, 2. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 5, Folder 77-80)
        - Belegstellen und Anmerkungen: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 5, Folder 81-82)
    - 1. Auflage, 2. Band
      - 4. Buch, 1.-3. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 5, Folder 83-86)
      - 5. Buch, 1.-3. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 5, Folder 87-89)
      - Envelope #193
        - 5. Buch, 3.-5. Kapitel und Anhang: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 5, Folder 90-94)
      - Envelope #190
        - 6. Buch, 1. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 5, Folder 95)
          See also: Oversize, Box 59, folder 1132
      - Envelope #193
        - 6. Buch, 2. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected (pp. 25-59), ca. 1906 (Box 5, Folder 96)
        - 6. Buch, 2. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected (pp. 60-98), ca. 1906 (Box 6, Folder 97)
        - 6. Buch, 3.-4. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 6, Folder 98-99)
          See also: Oversize, Box 59, folder 1133
        - 7. Buch, 1. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected (pp. 1-12), ca. 1906 (Box 6, Folder 100)
      - Envelope #190
        - 7. Buch, 1. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected (pp. 13-37), ca. 1906 (Box 6, Folder 101)
      - Envelope #193
        - 7. Buch, 1. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected (pp. 38-56), ca. 1906 (Box 6, Folder 102)
        - 7. Buch, 2. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 6, Folder 103)
        - Belegstellen und Anmerkungen: draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 6, Folder 104-07)
    - 1. Auflage, 1. u. 2 Bände
      - Envelope #190
        - Draft fragments, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 6, Folder 108-09)
      - Envelope #193
        - Draft fragments, holograph, corrected, ca. 1906 (Box 6, Folder 110-14)
    - 2. Auflage, 1. Band
      - Envelope #202
        - Inhalts-Verzeichnis: draft, holo- graph, printed pages of 1st ed. corrected for 2nd ed., ca. 1910 (Box 6, Folder 115)
        - Einleitung: draft, holograph, printed pages of 1st ed. cor- rected for 2nd ed., ca. 1910 (Box 6, Folder 116)
        - 1. Buch, 1. Kapitel: draft, holograph, printed pages cor- rected for 2nd ed., ca. 1910 (Box 6, Folder 117)
        - 1. Buch, 2.-3. Kapitel: draft, holograph, printed pages of 1st ed. corrected for 2nd ed., ca. 1910 (Box 7, Folder 118-20)
        - 2. Buch, 1.-2. Kapitel: draft, holograph, printed pages of 1st ed. corrected for 2nd ed., ca. 1910 (Box 7, Folder 121-23)
        - 3. Buch, 1.-2. Kapitel: draft, holograph, printed pages of 1st ed. corrected for 2nd ed., ca. 1910 (Box 7, Folder 124-25)
        - Belegstellen und Anmerkungen, draft, holograph, printed pages of first ed. corrected for 2nd ed., ca.1910 (Box 7, Folder 126)
    - 2. Auflage, 2. Band
      - Envelope #201
        - 4. Buch, 1.-2. Kapitel, draft, holograph, printed pages of 1st ed. corrected for 2nd ed., ca.1910 (Box 7, Folder 127-28)
        - 5. Buch, 1.-4. Kapitel, draft, holograph, printed pages of 1st ed. corrected for 2nd ed., ca. 1910 (Box 7, Folder 129-32)
        - 6. Buch, 1.-3. Kapitel, draft, holograph, printed pages of 1st ed. corrected for 2nd ed., ca. 1910 (Box 7, Folder 133-35)
        - 7. Buch, 1.- 4. Kapitel, draft, holograph, printed pages of 1st ed. corrected for 2nd ed., ca. 1910 (Box 7, Folder 136-39)
        - 8. Buch, 1.-2. Kapitel, draft, holograph, printed pages of 1st ed. corrected for 2nd ed., ca. 1910 (Box 8, Folder 140-41)
      - Envelope #108
        - Belegstellen und Anmerkungen, draft, holograph, printed pages of 1st ed. corrected for 2nd ed., ca. 1910 (Box 8, Folder 142)
    - 1. Auflage, 3. Band
      - Research notes, ca. 1919 (Box 8, Folder 143-46)
      - Envelope #195
        - Einleitung, drafts A-B, holographs, corrected, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 147-48)
        - 1. Kapitel, draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 149-51)
        - 2. Kapitel, draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 152-54)
        - 3. Kapitel, draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 155-56)
        - 4. Kapitel, draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 157-59)
        - 5. Kapitel, draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 160)
        - 6. Kapitel, draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 161)
        - 7. Kapitel, draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 162)
    - 1. Auflage, 4. Band
      - Envelope #146
        - Research notes, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 163-66)
      - Envelope #155
        - Research notes, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 167-74)
        - Research notes, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 175-76)
  - ESSAY ON MAN
    - Envelope #1
      - Outline and research notes (Box 10, Folder 177)
    - Envelope #43
      - Research notes, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 178)
    - Envelope #35
      - Aesthetics, research notes, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 179-80)
    - Envelope #57
      Introduction: Fundamental Types of Philosophical Anthropology, "Philo- sophical Answers to the Question What Is Man?, no published chapter]
      - Draft A, holograph, corrected, incomplete (pp. 1-128), n.d.
      - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 182)
      - Draft B, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 183)
      - Draft C, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 184)
    - Part I. What Is Man?
      [a.k.a. Book I. The Concept and the Task of a Philosophical Anthropology and First Part. The Problem and the Task of an Anthropological Philosophy]
      - Ch. I. "The Problem and the Method of a Philosophy of Symbolic Forms" [corresponds to no published chapter]
      - Envelope #75
        - Draft A, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 185)
      - Envelope #57
        - Draft B, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 186)
    - Part I. What Is Man?
      - Envelope #75
        - Ch. I. "The Historical Development and the Present Crisis of the Philosophy of Man": draft, holograph, corrected (pp. 1-63) [corresponds to no published chapter] (Box 10, Folder 187)
        - Ch. II. "The Sources and Methods of an Anthropological Philosophy": draft, holograph, corrected (pp. 64- 91) [corresponds to published Ch. I] (Box 10, Folder 188)
        - Ch. III. "In Quest of a Definition of Man": draft, holograph, corrected (pp. 92-101) [corresponds to published Ch. II] (Box 10, Folder 189)
        - Ch. IV. "Animal Reactions and Human Responses": draft, holograph, cor- rected (pp. 102-46) [corresponds to published Ch. III] (Box 10, Folder 190)
        - Ch. V. "Space and Time in the Human World": draft, holograph, corrected (pp. 147-187) [corresponds to published Ch. IV] (Box 10, Folder 191)
        - Ch. VI. "Actuality and Possibility": draft, holograph, corrected (pp. 187- 207) [corresponds to published Ch. V] (Box 10, Folder 192)
    - Part II. Man and Culture
      - Ch. I. "Myth and Religion": draft A, holograph, corrected (pp. 1-117) [corresponds to published Ch. VII] (Box 10, Folder 193)
      - Reste zum Mythos-Capital, einzulegen im 2. Durchschlag des Capitels: draft B, holograph, corrected (pp. 25a-28, 56-61) [corresponds to published Ch. VII] (Box 10, Folder 194)
      - Ch. I. "Language": draft A, holo- graph, corrected (pp. 1-80) [corresponds to published Ch. VIII] (Box 10, Folder 195)
      - Envelope #57
        - Ch. II. "Language" [corresponds to published Ch. VIII]
          - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 196)
          - Draft B, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 197)
      - Envelope #10
        - "Kunst," research notes [corresponds to published Ch. IX] (Box 11, Folder 198)
      - Envelope #57
        - Ch. III. "Art" [corresponds to pub- lished Ch. IX]
          - Draft A, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 199)
          - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 200)
      - Envelope #75
        - Ch. VII. "Art": draft C, holograph and typescript, corrected (pp. 1-83) [corresponds to published Ch. IX] (Box 11, Folder 201)
      - Envelope #3
        - Ch. IV, "History" [corresponds to published Ch. X]
          - Research notes, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 202)
          - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 203)
      - Envelope #75
        - Draft, holograph, corrected (pp. 1-96), n.d. (Box 11, Folder 204)
      - Envelope #25
        - "Science": draft A, holograph [corresponds to published Ch. XI] (Box 11, Folder 205)
      - Envelope #75
        - Ch. IV. "Science": draft B, holo- graph, corrected (pp. 1-42) [corresponds to published Ch. XI] (Box 11, Folder 206)
      - Envelope #57
        - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 207)
    - Part III. Symbol and Truth
      [a.k.a. Book III. Organic Reactions and Human Responses]
      - Envelope #75
        - Ch. I. "Pragmatic and Symbolic Behavior" [corresponds to no published chapter]
          - Draft A, holograph, corrected (pp. 141a-48, 153-63), n.d. (Box 11, Folder 208)
      - Envelope #57
        - Draft B, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 209)
      - Envelope #75
        - Ch. II. "Space and Time": draft, holograph, corrected (pp. 163a- 200) [corresponds to no published chapter] [N.B. on p. 200 Cassirer indicates that this chapter should follow Ch. III. "Tradition and Originality," Box 11, folders 215-16] (Box 11, Folder 210)
    - Part III. Symbol and Truth
      - Envelope #2
        - Ch. I, "Dogmatism and Scepticism" [corresponds to no published chapter]
          - Draft A, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 211)
          - Draft B, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 212)
        - Ch. II, "The Critical Solution" [corresponds to no published chapter]
          - Draft A, holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 11, Folder 213)
          - Draft B, typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 214)
        - Ch. III, "Tradition and Originality" [corresponds to no published chapter]
          - Draft A, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 215)
          - Draft B, typescript, corrected, and carbon (Box 11, Folder 216)
      - Envelope #25
        - Conclusion [corresponds to published Ch. XII]
          - Research notes, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 217)
      - Envelope #2
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 218)
        - Draft fragments, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 219)
  - FREIHEIT UND FORM
    - Envelope #192
      - Einleitung: draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 220)
      - Capitel I: draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 221-22)
      - Capitel II: draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 223)
      - Capitel III: draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 224)
      - Capitel IV: draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 225-27)
      - Capitel V: draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 228)
      - Capitel VI: draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 229-30)
  - DIE GESCHICHTE DER ANTIKEN PHILOSOPHIE
    - ERSTER TEIL. DIE PHILOSOPHIE DER GRIECHEN VON DEN ANFÄNGEN BIS PLATON von Ernst Cassirer
      - Envelope #189
        - Einleitung: draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 231)
        - I. "Die ionische Naturphilosophie": draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 232)
        - II. "Heraklit und die Pythagoreer": draft, holograph, corrected (Box 12, Folder 233)
        - III. "Die Eleaten": draft, holograph, corrected (Box 12, Folder 234)
          See also: Oversize, Box 59, folder 1134
        - IV. "Die jüngere Naturphilosophie (Empedokles, Anaxagoras und die Atomistik)": draft, holograph, corrected (Box 12, Folder 235)
          See also: Oversize, Box 59, folder 1135
        - V. "Die Sophistik": draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 236)
        - VI. "Sokrates": draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 237)
        - VII. "Platon": draft, holograph, corrected (Box 12, Folder 238-40)
          See also: Oversize, Box 59, folder 1136
        - "Die kleineren Sokratischen Schulen": draft, holograph, corrected (Box 13, Folder 241)
      - Envelope #112
        - Printed version, pp. 1-6, 77-134, 1925 (Box 13, Folder 242)
    - ZWEITER TEIL. DIE ANTIKE PHILOSOPHIE VON ARISTOTELES BIS ZUM AUSGANG DES ALTERTUMS von Ernst Hoffmann
      - Printed version, pp. 141-62, 1925 (Box 13, Folder 243)
  - GOETHE UND DIE GESCHICHTLICHEN WELT
    - Envelope #153
      - "Goethe und die geschichtlichen Welt": draft, holograph, corrected (Box 13, Folder 244)
    - Envelope #92
      - "Goethe und das 18. Jahrhundert": draft, holograph, corrected (Box 13, Folder 245)
    - Envelope #59
      - "Goethe und Platon": draft, offprint with printer's annotations (Box 13, Folder 246)
        See also: Box 39, folder 770
  - IDEE UND GESTALT
    - Envelope #178
      - Capitel I: draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 247)
      - Capitel II: draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 248-49)
      - Capitel III: draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 250)
    - Envelope #76
      - Capitel IV: draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 251)
    - Envelope #175
      - Capitel V: draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 252)
  - INDIVIDUUM UND KOSMOS
    - Envelope #60
      - Research notes, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 253-58)
    - Envelope #188
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 259-66)
  - KANTS LEBEN UND LEHRE
    - Envelope #105
      - Research notes, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 267-70)
    - Envelope #191
      - Kapitel I: draft, holograph, corrected, with printer's annotations, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 271)
      - Kapitel II: draft, holograph, corrected, with printer's annotations, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 272)
      - Kapitel II: draft, holograph, corrected, with printer's annotations, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 273)